Size William
Wallace'ı anlatacağım.
İngiliz tarihçiler benim bir
yalancı olduğumu söyleyecek.
Çünkü tarihi, kahramanları darağacında
sallandıranlar yazar.
İskoçya kralı öldüğünde,
bir oğlu yoktu,
ve İngiltere Kralı; Uzunbacaklı Edward
olarak tanınan zalim bir pagan,
kendini İskoçya Kralı
ilan etti.
İskoçya soyluları taht için hem kralla,
hem de kendi aralarında savaştılar.
Hal böyleyken Uzun bacaklı Edward, iskoç soylulara,
ateşkes toplantısı yapmak üzere onlara bir davet yolladı.
Silahsız bir toplantı olacaktı.
Sadece belgeler imzalanarak.
So Longshanks invited them
to talks of truce...
no weapons,
one page only.
Among the farmers of that shire
was Malcolm Wallace,
a commoner
with his own lands.
He had two sons...
John and William.
I told you to stay.
Well,
I finished my work.
Where are we going?
MacAndrews'.
He was supposed to visit
when the gathering
was over.
- Can I come?
- No, go home, boy.
But I want to go.
Go home or you'll feel
the back of my hand.
Go you home,
William.
MacAndrews!
Holy Jesus.
Aah!
It's all right!
William!
William, it's all right.
It's all right.
Easy, lad.
William.
Uhh!
And I say
we hit back now!
We cannot fight them!
It's suicide!
Wallace is right!
We fight them!
Every nobleman who had
a will to fight
was at that meeting.
We cannot beat
an army.
Not with 50 farmers.
We do not have
to beat them, just fight them.
Now, who's with me?
I am, Wallace.
All right, all right.
Ready.
Where do you think
you're going?
I'm going with you.
Ah, you're going
with me, are you?
And what are you
going to do?
I'm going to help.
Hey, and a good help
you'd be, too,
but I need you
to stay here
and look
after the place for me
while I'm away.
I can fight.
I know.
I know
you can fight.
But it's our wits
that make us men.
See you tomorrow.
Ha!
Hiya!
English.
Get down.
With your father
and brother gone,
they'll kill us
and burn the farm.
It's up to us, Hamish.
Nah.
Uhh!
Uhh. Ahh.
Da?
William.
Come here, lad.
Amen.
William.
I'm your uncle.
Argyle.
You have the look
of your mother.
Mmm.
We'll stay here tonight.
Tomorrow you'll
come home with me.
I don't want to leave.
You didn't want your father
to die either, did you?
But it happened.
Did the priest give
a poetic benediction?
"The Lord bless thee
and keep thee"?
It was in Latin.
You don't speak Latin?
Well, that's something
we shall have to remedy, isn't it?
The Lord
bless thee and keep thee.
The Lord cause His light
to shine on thee.
The Lord lift up
His countenance upon thee
and give thee peace.
Amen.
Your heart is free.
Have the courage
to follow it.
What are they doing?
Saying good-bye
in their own way...
playing outlawed tunes
on outlawed pipes.
It was the same for me
and your daddy
when our father
was killed.
First, learn to use...
this.
Then I'll teach you
to use...
this.
Many years later,
Edward the Longshanks,
King of England,
supervised the wedding
of his eldest son,
who would succeed him
to the throne.
Amen.
Asbride for his son,
Longshanks had chosen
the daughter of his rival,
the king of France.
It was widely whispered that
for the princess to conceive,
Longshanks would have to do
the honors himself.
That may have been
what he had in mind all along.
Scotland... my land.
The French will grovel
to anyone with strength,
but how will they
believe our strength
when we cannot rule
the whole of our own island?
Where is my son?
Your pardon, milord.
He asked me
to come in his stead.
I sent for him,
and he sends you.
Shall I leave, milord?
If he wants his queen
to rule when I am gone,
then, by all means,
stay and learn how.
Please.
Nobles.
Nobles are the key
to the door of Scotland.
Grant our nobles
lands in the north,
give their nobles
estates here in England,
and make them too greedy
to oppose us.
But, sire, our nobles
will be reluctant to uproot.
New lands
mean new taxes,
and they're already taxed
for the war in France.
Are they?
The trouble with Scotland
is that it's full of Scots.
Perhaps the time has come
to reinstitute
an old custom.
Grant them prima noctes.
First night.
When any common girl inhabiting
their lands is married,
our nobles shall have
sexual rights to her
on the night
of her wedding.
If we cart get them out,
we'll breed them out.
That should fetch
just the kind of lords
we want to Scotland,
taxes or no taxes, huh?
A most excellent
idea, sire.
Is it?
Now in Edinburgh gathered
the council of Scottish nobles.
Among these was Robert
the 17th earl of Bruce,
the leading contender
for the crown of Scotland.
Ah, I hear that Longshanks
has granted prima noctes.
Clearly meant to draw more
of his supporters here.
My father believes
that we must
lull Longshanks
into our confidence
by neither supporting his decree
nor opposing it.
A wise plan.
And how is your father?
We missed him at the council.
His affairs in France
keep him long overdue.
ve benim tüm Bruce'lari temsil ettigimi söyledi
ve ayrica Iskoçyayi.
But he sends his greetings,
and he says that I speak
for all of the Bruces
and for Scotland.
Ah, it's
all over now.
You've dropped
your rock.
Test of manhood.
You win.
Ah.
Call it a test
of soldiery, then.
The English won't let us
train with weapons,
so we train with stones.
The test of a soldier
is not in his arm.
It's here.
No. It's here.
Ha ha!
Hamish?
Mm-hmm.
Here you go, son.
Show him how.
Come on, Hamish!
Ha ha ha ha!
My boy!
That was a good throw.
Aye. Aye, it was.
I was wondering if you could
do that when it matters.
As it...
As it matters in battle.
Could you crush a man
with that throw?
I could crush you
like a worm.
Ooh!
You could?
Aye.
Well, then do it.
Would you like to see him
crush me like a worm?
Come do it.
You'll move.
I will not.
Right.
He'll move.
Come on, Hamish.
Come on there,
boy!
Well done!
Ah!
Fine display,
young Wallace.
Are you all right?
You look
a wee bit shaky.
I should have remembered
the rocks.
Aye, you should have.
Get up, you big heap.
It's good
to see you again.
Aye. Welcome home.
Oh, me head.
Oh, you should
have moved.
William...
will you dance
with me?
Of course I will.
I've come to claim
the right of prima noctes.
As lord of these lands,
I will
bless this marriage
by taking the bride
into my bed
on the first night
of her union.
Oh, by God,
you will not!
It is my noble right.
Good evening, sin'.
Ah, young Wallace.
Grand soft evening, huh?
Aye, it's that.
I was wondering if I might have
a word with your daughter.
What do you want
to have a word about?
Well, um...
Murron, would you like
to come and ride with me
on this fine evening?
In this?
You're out of your mind.
It's good
Scottish weather, madame.
The rain is falling
straight down.
Well, slightly
to the side, like.
She cart go with you.
No the now, anyway.
No the now.
- No the now?
- We'll see you later.
The weather's just fine.
It's hardly raining.
Did you not hear
what I said?
Murron! Get... Oh.
It's you she takes after.
How could you know me
after so long?
Well, I didn't.
I saw you staring,
and I didn't know who you were.
I'm sorry.
I suppose I was.
Are you in the habit
of riding off in the rain
with strangers?
It was the best way
to make you leave.
Well, if I can ever work up
the courage to ask you again,
I'll send
written warning first.
Wouldn't do much good.
I cart read.
Can you not?
No.
Well, that's something
we shall have to remedy,
isn't it?
You're going to
teach me to read, then?
If you like.
In what language?
You're showing off now.
That's right.
Are you impressed yet?
No. Why should I be?
Do that standing on your head,
and I'll be impressed.
My kilt will fly up,
but I'll try it.
God, you certainly
didn't learn any manners.
The French and Romans
have far worse manners.
You've been to Rome?
Aye. Argyle took me
on a pilgrimage.
What was it like?
What does that mean?
Beautiful.
But I belong here.
Murron?
Come in now.
Sin', I know it was
strange of me
to invite Murron
to ride last night,
but I assure you...
Mac Clannough's daughter
is another matter.
I've come to fetch you
to our meeting.
What kind
of meeting?
The secret kind.
Your meetings are
a waste of time, Campbell.
Your father was a fighter
and a patriot.
I know
who my father was.
I came back home
to raise crops
and, God willing,
a family.
If I can live
in peace, I will.
Go on.
You say you want
to stay out of the troubles?
If you can prove it,
you may court my daughter.
Until you prove it,
my answer's no.
No?
No, Wallace. No.
Didn't I just prove it?
No!
No?
Uh!
Of course, running a farm's
a lot of work,
but that will all change
when my sons arrive.
So you've
got children?
Oh, not yet,
but I was hoping
that you could
help me with that.
So you want me
to marry you, then?
Well, it's a bit sudden,
but all right.
Is that what you call
a proposal?
I love you.
Always have.
I want to marry you.
Is that a "yes"?
Aye, that's a "yes. "
It is?
We best hurry.
He'll be waiting.
Oh, wait.
Where are you going?
What's that?
You'll see.
Father.
I will love you
my whole life,
you and no other.
And I you,
you and no other,
forever.
When am I going
to see you again?
Tonight?
I cart.
Why not?
My dad's growin'
suspicious.
Growin' suspicious,
is he?
Wouldn't have anything
to do with that.
When? When? When?
When?
Tonight.
Look lively,
Sergeant.
Where are you
going, lassie?
Ooh, that
looks heavy.
Let me help you
with it.
No. It's fine.
I'm not going
to steal it.
Oh, you remind me
of my daughter back home.
Hello, lassie.
Aah!
No!
Shh! Shh!
Keep it quiet, Smythe.
Ah!
You bitch!
Aah!
Aah! You...
bitch!
Are you all right?
All right?
Come on.
Are you all right?
Aye.
Can you ride?
Come back here,
you bastard!
Raise the alarm!
Help!
Meet me
at the grove.
Ride!
They're
getting away!
Go round back!
Get him!
Come on!
Ah!
Murron?
Murron!
All of you know
full well
the great pains
I've always taken
never to be too strict,
too rigid
with the application
of our laws,
and as a consequence,
have we not learned
to live together
in relative peace
and harmony?
Huh?
And this day's lawlessness
is how you repay
my leniency!
Well, you leave me
with little choice.
An assault
on the king's soldiers...
is the same as an assault
on the king himself.
Now...
Let this scrapper
come to me.
Sin'!
There.
Aah!
Argh!
Ahh!
Corporal.
Some archers
on the tower now!
Ah! Aah...
Hold still.
Aah!
You idiot boy!
Argh!
Aah!
Unh!
Father,
how are you?
Unh.
Macaulish.
Macaulish!
Macaulish! Macaulish!
Wallace! Wallace! Wallace!
What you waiting
for, boy?
Here. You can do it.
I'll hold him down.
Here.
You can do it.
I'll hold him down.
Pour it straight
in the wound.
It seems like a waste
of good whiskey.
Indulge me. Ah!
Aah!
Hold him.
Now let him go.
Aah!
I'm sorry.
That'll wake you up
in the morning, boy.
There's somebody coming!
Arm yourselves!
There's somebody coming.
MacGregors...
from the next clan.
We heard about
what was happening.
We don't want
you amadans
thinking you can
have your fun without us.
Go home.
Some of us
are in this.
Cart help that now.
But you can help
yourselves.
Go home.
We'll have
no homes left
when the English garrison
from the castle
comes through
and burns us out.
And they will.
Welcome.
Patrol returning,
milord!
So what news?
I have dispatched
100 soldiers to Lanark.
They will be
returning now!
What, are they
dressed like this?
Actually,
it was more like 50.
Make it quick.
You remember me?
I never did her
any harm.
It was my right.
Your right?
I'm here to claim the right
of a husband!
Ah!
I am William Wallace.
And the rest of you
will be spared.
Go back to England
and tell them there
that Scotland's daughters
and her sons are yours no more.
Tell them Scotland is free.
Burn it.
The Scottish rebels
have routed
one of my garrisons
and murdered
the noble lord.
I heard.
This Wallace is a brigand,
nothing more.
And how would you deal
with this brigand?
Like any common thief.
Have the local
magistrate arrest him
and punish him
accordingly.
Leave us.
Wallace has already
killed the magistrate
and taken control
of the town.
Stand up.
In the morning,
I depart for France
to press our rights there,
and I leave you here to
quell this little rebellion.
Understood?
Is it?
Unh!
One day,
you will be a king.
At least
try to act like one.
Get away from me!
Convene my military council.
Aah!
There!
After them.
No point resisting.
You're outnumbered
and trapped.
Now, where are the rest of you?
Where's Wallace?
Father?
Oh, come in.
Come in.
A rebellion
has begun.
Under whom?
A commoner...
named William Wallace.
You will embrace
this rebellion.
Suppon't it from
our lands in the north.
I will gain
English favor
by condemning it
and ordering it opposed
from our lands
in the south.
Sit down.
Stay awhile.
This Wallace...
he doesn't even
have a knighthood,
but he fights
with passion,
and he inspires.
And you wish to charge off
and fight as he did, eh?
So would I.
Well, maybe it's time.
It is time...
to survive.
You're the 17th
Roben't Bruce.
The 16 before you
passed you land and title
because they didn't
charge in.
Call a meeting
of the nobles.
They do nothing
but talk.
Rightly so.
They're as rich
in English titles and lands
as they are in Scottish,
just as we are.
You admire this man,
this William Wallace.
Uncompromising men
are easy to admire.
He has courage.
So does a dog.
But it is exactly
the ability to compromise
that makes a man noble.
And understand this...
Edward Longshanks
is the most ruthless king
ever to sit
on the throne of England,
and none of us
and nothing of Scotland
will remain
unless we are as ruthless.
Give ear to our nobles.
Knowing their minds
is the key
to the throne.
Wait. Wait.
Look.
This is out,
and this is left.
Carry on.
Carry on!
You know...
eventually,
Longshanks will send
his whole northern army
against us.
Heavy cavalry,
armored horse...
shake the very ground.
They'll ride
right over us.
Uncle Argyle used to
talk about it,
how no army ever stood up
to a charge of heavy horse.
So what do we do?
Hit, run, hide,
the Highland way.
We'll make spears.
Hundreds of them.
Long spears...
twice as long as a man.
That long?
Aye.
Some men are longer
than others.
Your mother been telling you
stories about me again.
Volunteers coming in!
William Wallace,
we've come to fight
and to die for you.
Stand up, man.
I'm not the pope.
My name is Faudron.
My sword is yours.
I brought you this.
We checked them for arms.
My wife made it
for you.
Thank you.
Him? That cart
be William Wallace.
I'm prettier
than this man.
All right, Father.
I'll ask him.
If I risk
my neck for you,
will I get a chance
to kill Englishmen?
Is your father
a ghost,
or do you converse
with the Almighty?
To find his equal,
an Irishman talks to God.
The Almighty says
don't change the subject.
Just answer
the fucking question.
Mind your tongue.
Insane Irish.
Smart enough to get a dagger
past your guards, old man.
That's my friend,
Irishman,
and the answer
to your question is yes.
You fight for me,
you get to kill the English.
Excellent!
Stephen is my name.
I'm the most wanted
man on my island,
except I'm not on my island,
of course.
More's the pity.
Your island?
You mean Ireland?
Yeah. It's mine.
You're a madman.
Ha ha ha!
I've come to
the right place, then.
Aah!
Sure didn't the Almighty
send me to watch your back?
I didn't like him
anyway.
He wasn't right
in the head.
It's several runners!
Hello.
The English are advancing
an army toward Stirling.
Do the nobles
rally?
Roben't the Bruce
and most of the others
will not commit
to battle,
but word has spread,
and the Highlanders
are coming down on their own.
In droves of hundreds
and thousands.
Are you ready
for a war?
What news?
We're outnumbered,
at least three to one.
How many horse?
300. Maybe more.
300 heavy horse?
We must negotiate.
Who's in command?
Did he have
a scarlet chevron?
Aye, he did.
We can still
negotiate.
What are they
talking about?
I cart hear,
but it does not look good.
The nobles
will negotiate.
They'll do
a deal,
then we go home.
If not,
we charge.
We have no chance.
So many.
I didn't come here
to fight
so they could own
more lands.
Then I'll have to
work for them.
Nor me.
All right, lads!
I'm not dying for these bastards.
Let's go home!
Stop, men!
Do not flee!
Wait until
we've negotiated!
William Wallace.
Cart be.
Not tall enough.
The Almighty says this must be
a fashionable fight.
It's drawn
the finest people.
Where is thy salute?
For presenting yourselves
on this battlefield,
I give you thanks.
This is our army.
To join it,
you give homage.
I give homage to Scotland,
and if this is your army...
why does it go?
We didn't come here
to fight for them!
Home!
The English are too many.
Sons of Scotland...
I am William Wallace.
William Wallace
is 7 feet tall.
Yes. I've heard.
He kills men
by the hundreds,
and if he were here,
he'd consume the English
with fireballs
from his eyes
and bolts of lightning
from his arse.
I am William Wallace...
and I see a whole army
of my countrymen
here in defiance
of tyranny.
You've come to fight
as free men.
And free men you are.
What will you do
with that freedom?
Will you fight?
- No!
- No.
Against that?
No!
We will run,
and we will live.
Aye.
Fight, and you may die.
Run, and you'll live...
at least awhile.
And dying in your beds
many years from now,
would you be willing
to trade
all the days
from this day to that
for one chance...
just one chance...
to come back here
and tell our enemies
that they may take
our lives,
but they'll never take
our freedom?
Albagu bra!
They seem quite
optimistic to me.
Maybe they do
want to fight.
Confrontation might be
a foregone conclusion, milord,
but, nonetheless,
I think we should deliver
the king's terms.
The king's terms?
He'll never live up to them.
Milord, I think...
All right.
Offer them the terms.
Shall we go and meet them?
Let me do the talking.
Agreed.
Fine speech.
Now what do we do?
Just be yourselves.
Where are you going?
I'm going to pick
a fi ght.
Hyah!
Well, we didn't get dressed up
for nothing.
Mornay, Lochlan, Craig.
Here are
the king's terms...
Lead this army
off the field...
and he will give you each
estates in Yorkshire,
including
hereditary title,
from which you will pay...
from which you will pay him
an annual duty...
I have an offer
foryou.
Cheltham, this is
William Wallace.
From which you will pay
the king an annual duty...
I said I have
an offer foryou.
You disrespect
a banner oftruce?
From his king?
Absolutely.
Here are
Scotland's terms...
Loweryour flags
and march
straight back
to England,
stopping at every home
you pass by
to beg forgiveness
for 100 years oftheft,
rape, and murder.
Do that,
and your men shall live.
Do it not, and every one
of you will die today.
Ha ha ha ha!
You are outmatched.
You have no
heavy cavalry.
In two centuries,
no army has won...
I'm not finished!
Before we let you leave,
your commander
must cross that field,
present himself
before this army,
put his head
between his legs,
and kiss his own arse.
I'd say that was rather
less cordial than he's used to.
Be ready and do
exactly as I say.
On my signal,
ride round behind our position
and flank them.
We must not
divide our forces.
Do it, and let the English
see you do it.
They'll think
we run away.
Take out their archers.
I'll meet you in the middle.
Right.
Come on.
Hyah!
Insolent bastard.
I want this Wallace's
heart on a plate.
Archers.
Archers! Archers!
Archers!
Archers, forward!
Aah!
You bastards!
Loose!
The Lord tells me
he can get me out of this mess,
but He's pretty sure
you're fucked.
Ha ha ha!
Aah!
Ready!
Loose!
Ride!
See. Every Scot with a horse
is fleeing.
Our cavalry will ride
them down like grass.
Send the horse.
Full attack.
Steady!
Hold!
Now!
Send the infantry.
You lead them!
Aah!
Retreat!
Bastard!
All right.
Aah!
Wallace! Wallace!
I knight thee
Sire William Wallace.
Sire William,
in the name of God,
we declare
and appoint thee
guardian and high protector
of Scotland
and thy captains
as aides-de-camp.
Stand and be recognized.
Does anyone know
his politics?
No, but his weight
with the commoners
could unbalance
everything.
The Balliols
will kiss his arse,
and so we must.
Sire William.
Sire William...
inasmuch as you
and your captains
hail from a region
long known to support
the Balliol clan,
may we invite you
to continue your support
and uphold
our rightful claim.
Damn the Balliol clan!
They're all
Longshanks' men!
Gentlemen.
Now is the time
to declare a king.
You're prepared to recognize
our legitimate succession?
You're the ones who won't
suppon't the rightful...
Those were lies...
Oh, no.
That's the truth.
I demand recognition
of these documents!
These documents were lies
when you wrote them!
Gentlemen, please!
Gentlemen!
Please, gentlemen!
Wait! Sire William,
where are you going?
We have beaten
the English,
but they'll come back
because you
won't stand together.
What will you do?
I will invade England
and defeat the English
on their own ground.
Ha ha ha! Invade?
That's impossible.
Why?
Why is that impossible?
You're so concerned
with squabbling
for the scraps
from Longshanks' table
that you've missed
your God-given right
to something better.
There's a difference
between us.
You think the people
of this country exist
to provide you
with position.
I think your
position exists
to provide those people
with freedom,
and I go to make sure
that they have it.
Wait!
I respect
what you said,
but remember
that these men
have lands
and castles.
It's much to risk.
The common man that bleeds
on the battlefield...
does he risk less?
No...
but from top to bottom,
this country has got
no sense of itself.
Its nobles share
allegiance with England.
Its clans
war with each other.
Aye.
If you make enemies
on both sides of the border,
you'll end up dead.
We all end up dead.
It's just a question
of how and why.
I want
what you want,
but we need
the nobles.
We need them?
Aye.
Nobles.
Tell me, what does that mean...
to be noble?
Your title
gives you claim
to the throne
of our country,
but men
don't follow titles,
they follow courage.
Now, our people
know you.
Noble and common...
they respect you,
and if you would
just lead them to freedom...
they'd follow you.
And so would I.
Damn it!
My sodomite cousin
the prince tells me
he has no troops
to lend,
and every town in Northern England
is begging for help.
He advances!
To which town?
To here, milord.
Bring the provisions
inside!
Double the wall guards!
Seal the gate! Now!
Hyah!
Bring in the provisions!
Sire, we can get you out
if you leave now.
I'm not about
to tell my uncle
I've lost him the greatest city
in Northern England.
Come on!
Make way for the king!
It's not your fault.
Stand up to him!
I will stand up
to him and more.
What news of the north?
Nothing new,
Your Majesty.
We've sent riders
to speed any word.
I heard the word
in France,
where I was fighting
to expand your future kingdom.
The word, my son,
is that our entire
northern army is annihilated...
and you have done nothing.
L- I have ordered
conscriptions.
They're assembled
and ready to depart.
Excuse me, sire, but there's
a very urgent message from York.
Come.
Leave us.
Thank you, sire.
Uh, W-Wallace has
sacked York.
What?
Wallace has sacked York.
Uh!
Oh.
Sire...
thy own nephew.
What beast could do
such a thing?
If he can sack York...
he can invade
Lower England.
We would stop him!
Who is this person
who speaks to me
as though I needed
his advice?
I have declared Phillip
my high counselor.
Is he qualified?
I am skilled
in the arts of war
and military tactics,
sire.
Are you?
Then tell me...
what advice would you offer
on the, uh,
present, uh,
situation?
Aah!
I shall offer a truce...
and buy him off.
But who will go to him?
Not I.
If I fell under the sword
of that murderer,
it might be my head
in a basket.
And not my gentle son.
The mere sight of him
would only encourage an enemy
to take over the whole country.
So whom do I send?
Whom do I send?
I'm dreaming.
Yes, you are.
And you must wake.
Uh...
I don't want to wake.
I want to stay here
with you.
And I with you...
but you must wake now.
Wake up, William.
Wake up.
William, wake up,
wake up.
William!
A royal entourage comes!
Flying banners of truce!
And the standards
of Longshanks himself!
I am the princess
of Wales.
I come as
the king's servant
and with
his authority.
To do what?
To discuss
the king's proposals.
Will you speak
with a woman?
I understand you have recently
been given the rank of knight.
I have been given
nothing.
God makes men
what they are.
Did God make you the sacker
of peaceful cities?
The executioner
of the king's nephew,
my husband's own cousin?
York was
the staging point
for every invasion
of my country,
and that royal cousin
hanged innocent Scots,
even women and children
from the city walls.
Well, Longshanks
did far worse
the last time he took
a Scottish city.
You ask your king
to his face.
Ask him.
You see if his eyes
can convince you of the truth.
Hamilton, leave us.
Milady...
Leave us. Now.
Let us talk plainly.
You invade England,
but you cannot
complete the conquest
so far from your shelter
and supply.
The king desires peace.
Longshanks
desires peace?
He declares it to me.
I swear it.
He proposes that
you withdraw your attack.
In return, he grants you
title, estates,
and this chest of gold,
which I am to pay
to you personally.
A lordship and titles...
gold...
that I should become
Judas?
Peace is made
in such ways.
Slaves are made
in such ways!
The last time
Longshanks spoke of peace,
I was a boy,
and many
Scottish nobles,
who would not be slaves,
were lured by him,
under a flag of truce,
to a barn... where
he had them hanged.
I was very young,
but I remember
Longshanks' notion of peace.
I understand
you have suffered.
I know... about your woman.
She was my wife.
We married in secret
because I would not share her
with an English lord.
They killed her...
to get to me.
I have never
spoken of it.
I don't know why
I tell you now,
except...
I see her strength
in you.
One day,
you'll be a queen...
And you must
open your eyes.
You tell your king
that William Wallace
will not be ruled...
and nor will any Scot
while I live.
Ah, my son's
loyal wife returns
unkilled
by the heathen.
So he accepted
our bribe?
No, he did not.
Then why does he stay?
My scouts tell me that
he has not advanced.
He waits for you at York.
He says he will attack
no more towns or cities
if you are man enough
to come and face him.
Did he?
The Welsh bowmen
will not be detected
arriving so far
around his flank.
The main force
of our armies from France
will land here
to the north of Edinburgh.
Conscripts from Ireland will
approach from the southwest...
to here.
Welsh bowmen? Troops from France?
Irish conscripts?
Even if you
dispatch them today,
they'd take weeks
to assemble.
I dispatched them
before I sent your wife.
So our little ruse
succeeded.
Thank you.
And while
this upstart
awaits my arrival
in York,
my forces will have arrived
in Edinburgh behind him.
You spoke with this,
uh, Wallace in private.
Tell me...
what kind of man
is he?
A mindless barbarian.
Not a king like you,
milord.
You may return
to your embroidery.
Humbly, milord.
You brought back the money,
of course.
No. I gave it
to ease the suffering
of the children
of this war.
That's what happens
when you send a woman.
Forgive me, sire.
I thought that generosity
might demonstrate
your greatness
to those
you mean to rule.
Ahem.
My greatness will be
better demonstrated
when Wallace
returns to Scotland
and finds his country
in ashes.
William!
There's riders
approaching!
Personal escort
of the princess.
Aye.
Must have made
an impression.
Aye.
I didn't think you were
in the tent that long.
Mademoiselle.
Un message
de ma maitresse.
Merci.
It's true! English ships
are moving up from the south!
I don't know about
the Welsh yet,
but the Irish
have landed!
I had to see it
before I could believe it.
Why are the Irish
fighting with the English?
I wouldn't worry
about them.
Didn't I tell you before?
It's my island.
Hamish, ride ahead
to Edinburgh
and assemble
the council.
Order it.
Aye.
Hup!
Hyah!
Your island?
My island! Yup!
You want to negotiate?
No, please,
gentlemen!
Lords,
Craig is right!
This time
our only option
is to negotiate.
Unless you want to see Edinburgh
razed to the ground...
My army has marched
for more days
than I can remember,
and we still have
preparations to make,
so I'll make this plain.
We require every soldier
you can summon...
your personal escorts,
even yourselves...
and we need them now.
With such a force
arrayed against us,
it's time to discuss
other options.
Other options?
Don't you wish at least
to lead your men
onto the field
and barter a better deal
with Longshanks
before you tuck tail
and run?
Sire William...
We cart defeat
this army!
We can!
And we will!
We won at Stirling...
and still you quibble!
We won at York,
and you would not support us.
If you'll not
stand up with us now,
then I say
you're cowards.
And if you're Scotsmen,
I'm ashamed
to call myself one.
Please, Sire William,
speak with me alone.
I beg you.
Now, you've achieved more
than anyone ever dreamed,
but fighting
these odds,
it looks like rage,
not courage.
It's well beyond rage.
Help me.
In the name of Christ,
help yourselves!
Now is our chance. Now.
If we join, we can win.
If we win, we'll have
what none of us ever had before...
a country of our own.
You're the rightful leader.
And there is strength in you,
I see it.
Unite us.
Unite us!
Unite the clans.
All right.
Right.
This cannot be the way.
You said yourself...
the nobles will not
support Wallace.
So how did it help us
to join the side
that is slaughtered?
I gave him my word.
I know it is hard.
Being a leader is.
But, son... son...
look at me.
I cannot be king.
You and you alone
can rule Scotland.
What I tell you,
you must do.
Not for me,
not for yourself,
for your country.
Eh, lads, make way.
Coming through here.
Make way, lads.
Make...
The Bruce is
not coming, William.
He'll come.
Mornay and Lochlan
have come.
So will the Bruce.
Quite the lovely...
gathering.
Wouldn't you agree?
The archers
are ready, sire.
Not the archers.
My scouts tell me
their archers are miles away
and no threat to us.
Arrows cost money.
Use up the Irish.
The dead cost nothing.
And send in
the infantry and cavalry.
Infantry!
Cavalry!
Advance!
Ah, good to see you
this morning!
Irish.
Glad to
have you with us.
Watch this.
Mornay? Lochlan?
I gave Mornay double
his lands in Scotland
and matching estates
in England.
Lochlan turned
for much less.
Archers.
I beg pardon, sire.
Won't we hit
our own troops?
Yes...
but we'll hit theirs
as well.
We have reserves.
Attack.
Archers!
Archers... attack!
Loose!
Send in our reinforcements.
Send in the rest!
Bring me Wallace.
Alive, if possible.
Dead... just as good.
Send us news
of our victory.
Shall we retire?
Protect the king.
Get up!
Up!
Get him out of here!
Go!
I'm dying.
Let me be.
No.
You're going to live.
I've lived long enough
to live free.
Proud to see you become
the man you are.
I'm a happy man.
I'm the one
who's rotting,
but I think your face
looks graver than mine.
Son...
we must have alliance
with England
to prevail here.
You achieved that.
You saved your family,
increased your land.
In time, you will have
all the power in Scotland.
Lands, titles,
men, power... nothing.
Nothing?
I have nothing.
Men fight for me...
because if they do not,
I throw them off my land
and I starve their wives
and their children.
Those men who bled
the ground red at Falkirk...
they fought for
William Wallace,
and he fights for
something that I've never had.
And I took it from him
when I betrayed him,
and I saw it in his face
on the battlefield,
and it's tearing me apart!
Well, all men betray,
all lose heart.
I don't want
to lose heart!
I want to believe...
as he does.
I will never be
on the wrong side again.
No!
There he is!
After him!
Lord Craig,
is it true about Mornay?
Aye. Wallace rode into his bedchamber
and killed him.
More a liability now
than ever he was.
And there's no telling
who'll be next.
Maybe you.
Maybe me.
It doesn't matter.
I'm serious, Robert.
So am I!
Christ! Shit!
Search the place!
Lochlan.
William Wallace
killed 50 men.
50 if it was one.
100 men...
with his own sword.
Cut through them like...
Moses through
the Red Sea.
His legend grows.
It will be worse
than before.
He rallies new volunteers
in every Scottish town,
and when he replenishes
his numbers...
They're sheep!
Mere sheep!
Easily dispersed
if we strike the shepherd.
Very well.
Pick a flock
of your finest assassins
and set a meeting.
Milord, Wallace
is renowned
for his ability
to smell an ambush.
If what Lord Hamilton tells me
is correct,
he warmed to
our future queen.
He would trust her.
So we'll dispatch her
with the notion
that she comes in peace.
Milord, the princess
might be taken hostage
or her life
be put in jeopardy.
Oh, my son would be
most distressed by that.
Uh, but in truth,
if she were to be killed,
we would soon find
the king of France
a useful ally
against the Scots.
You see, as king,
you must find the good
in any situation.
It's William Wallace, sure.
He's giving up his sword.
Be ready.
Aah!
Milady...
I received your message.
Oh.
This is...
the second time
you've warned me
of danger.
Why?
There will be
a new shipment of supplies
coming north next month...
foods and weapons.
No, stop.
Why do you help me?
Because of the way
you are looking at me now.
Just when we thought
all hope was lost,
our noble saviors
have arrived.
Off with their... hoods.
Sire William, we've come
to seek a meeting.
Well, what's the point?
You've all sworn loyalty
to Longshanks.
An oath to a liar
is no oath at all.
Every man of us is ready
to swear loyalty to you.
So let the council
swear publicly.
We cannot. Some scarcely
believe you're alive.
Others think you'll pay
them Mornay's wages.
So we bid you
to Edinburgh.
Meet us two days
from now.
Pledge us your pardon,
and we'll unite behind you.
Scotland will be one.
One?
You mean us and you.
No.
I mean this.
It's the pledge
of Robert the Bruce.
You do know it's a trap.
Tell him.
If the Bruce
wanted to kill you,
he'd have done it
at Falkirk.
Aye.
I know. I saw.
Leave him aside.
What about the others?
Nest of scheming bastards!
They couldn't agree
on the color of shite!
It's a trap.
Are you blind?
Look at us.
We've got to try.
We cart do
this alone.
Joining the nobles
is the only hope for our people.
You know what happens
if we don't take that chance?
What?
Nothing.
I don't want
to be a martyr.
Nor I.
I want to live.
I want a home
and children and peace.
Do you?
Aye, I do.
I've asked God
for those things.
It's all for nothing
if you don't have freedom.
That's just
a dream, William.
A dream?
Just a...
Well, then what have we
been doing all this time?
We've lived that dream.
Your dream
isn't about freedom.
It's about Murron.
Your dream is to be a hero
'cause you think she sees you.
I don't think she sees me.
I know she does.
And your father
sees you, too.
Ohh!
Ah.
Jesus.
Get up.
Give us your hand.
Shall I come with you?
No. I'll go alone.
I'll see you after.
Right.
Sooner rather
than later, I hope.
He won't come.
He will.
I know he will.
Milord,
he approaches!
No!
Stay out of it,
Robert!
Aah!
You lied! You lied!
Bruce is not to be hurt!
That's the arrangement!
Father!
You rotting bastard!
Why? Why?
Longshanks
acquired Wallace.
So did our nobles.
That was the price
of your crown.
Die!
I want you to die!
Soon enough I'll be dead,
and you'll be king.
I don't want
anything from you.
You're not a man!
You're not my father.
You're my son,
and you've always known my mind.
You deceived me.
You let yourself
be deceived.
In your heart, you always knew
what had to happen here.
Thus, you know what
it means to hate.
Now you're ready
to be a king.
My hate will die...
with you.
William Wallace,
you stand in taint
of high treason.
Against whom?
Against your king.
Have you
anything to say?
Never in my whole life...
did I swear
allegiance to him.
It matters not.
He is your king.
Confess, and you may
receive a quick death.
Deny, and you must
be purified by pain.
Do you confess?
Then on the morrow,
you shall receive
your purification.
Your Highness.
I will see the prisoner.
We've got orders
from the king...
The king will be
dead in a month.
His son
is a weakling.
Who do you think
will rule this kingdom?
Now open this door.
Majesty.
Come on, filth.
Up on your feet.
Stop it!
Leave me.
I said, leave me!
Milady.
Sire, I come
to beg you...
to confess all
and swear allegiance to the king
that he might
show you mercy.
Will he show mercy
to my country?
Mercy is
to die quickly,
perhaps even
live in a tower.
In time, who knows
what can happen...
if you can only live?
If I swear to him,
then all that I am
is dead already.
You will die.
It will be awful.
Every man dies.
Not every man really lives.
Drink this.
It will dull
your pain.
No. It will numb
my wits.
I must have them all.
For if I'm senseless,
or if I wail,
then Longshanks
will have broken me.
I cart bear the thought
of your torture.
Take it.
All right.
I have come to beg
for the life of William Wallace.
You're quite taken
with him, aren't you?
I respect him.
At worst,
he was a worthy enemy.
Show mercy,
O thou great king,
and win the respect
of your own people.
Even now...
you are incapable of mercy.
And you...
To you, that word is
as unfamiliar as love.
Before he lost
his powers of speech,
he told me his
one comfort was that
he would live to know
Wallace was dead.
You see...
death comes to us all.
But before
it comes to you,
know this...
Your blood dies with you.
A child who is not of your line
grows in my belly.
Your son will not sit long
on the throne, I swear it.
I'm so afraid.
Give me the strength...
to die well.
Here he comes!
Now behold
the awful price of treason!
You will fall
to your knees now.
Declare yourself
the king's loyal subject
and beg his mercy.
And you shall have it.
Rope!
Stretch him!
That's it!
Shame! Shame!
Pleasant... yes?
Rise to your knees,
kiss the royal emblem
on my cloak,
and you will feel
no more.
Rack him!
Ahh.
Enough?
Ohh.
It can all end
right now.
Peace.
Just say it.
Cry out... mercy.
Mercy!
- Mercy!
Cry out.
Just say it...
mercy.
- Mercy!
Mercy, William.
Mercy.
Jesus, now say it.
The prisoner wishes
to say a word.
- Mercy!
Mercy!
Freeeedoooom!
After the beheading,
William Wallace's body
was torn to pieces.
His head was set
on London Bridge,
his arms and legs sent
to the four corners of Britain
as a warning.
It did not have the effect
that Longshanks planned.
Andl... Robert the Bruce...
rode out topay homage to
the armies of the English king
and accept
his endorsement of my crown.
I hope you've washed
your arse this morning.
It's about to be
kissed by a king.
Come. Let's get it over with.
Stop!
You have bled
with Wallace!
Now bleed with me.
Oh...
Aah!
Wallace! Wallace!
Wallace!
In the year of our Lord, 1314,
patriots of Scotland,
starving and outnumbered,
charged the fields
of Bannockburn.
They fought like warrior poets,
they fought like Scotsmen...
and won their freedom